Okay, I guess it must be a nice day
outside. Uh, it's nice to see everyone.
Um, okay. So today we're going to finish
up some stuff on uh rational decisions
and uh we'll look at decision networks
which is how we extend basets to include
uh both actions and utility information
so that with that decision network you
can uh simply ask it to make rational
decisions. uh and then we'll talk about
something called the value of
information
uh which is how useful is it to obtain
the value of an unobserved variable in a
probability model. Um and we'll see that
in fact the decision network can answer
that question as well. So not only can
it make the optimal decision given the
information that it has uh it can also
decide what is the next best piece of
information to get uh or even what's the
best sequence of information to seek. Um
and then when we're done with that uh
we'll start on machine learning. Um
we'll cover
well in theory we'll cover decision
trees and linear regression. Uh my guess
is we'll have to probably push linear
regression to next time. Okay. So um
uh we're going to talk about a very a
very simplified decision situation where
um someone needs to figure out should I
take my umbrella to work, okay, or to
school or whatever it might be, right?
And this is something that we often have
to to think about. And um obviously
there's some benefit to taking it if it
rains, but it's kind of a pain to lug it
around and you usually lose it if it
doesn't rain. Uh you leave it somewhere
and then you're annoyed. Um of course,
if you leave it home and it does rain,
that's also maybe even worse. So these
are the kinds of things that you might
be thinking about. Um, and so the the
right decision depends on the weather,
but of course you don't know what the
weather is going to be. Uh, but maybe
you can get some information from the
weather forecast.
So that's that's the situation. It's
very very simple. Um, and I should be on
this slide. Um,
okay. So decision networks extend basets
by adding two new kinds of nodes. Uh,
the rectangular nodes are actions.
And so this here the uh you can take the
umbrella or not right. So a twovalued
action variable
and um also a utility variable. So a
utility variable describes uh the value
uh to the decision maker uh as a
function of the values of the parent
variables.
Right? So in this case uh what this
decision network says is that uh my
utility depends on whether I take my
umbrella and what the weather is. It
doesn't depend on what the forecast says
given that I know what the weather is
and so we don't have right there's no
link from forecast to directly to the
utility. So my utility depends on the
actual weather. But of course I may not
know the actual weather. And so that's
where the the baset part of this comes
in handy because it can do the inference
to tell me what the probability of the
different uh weather states uh might be.
Um and then using information about the
probability of the weather and the
decision that I make about the umbrella,
I can figure out the expected utility of
each of those decisions. Okay. So
uh so this just says what I just said.
So decision networks are basets plus
action nodes plus utility nodes.
Okay. Um so action nodes right because
they are things you are going to choose
it. They typically don't have any
parents.
And um what the algorithm is going to do
is you're not trying to figure out
what's the most likely action or what's
the probability that I'll take such and
such an action. You're going to choose
the action. So the algorithm is going to
basically iterate through the possible
actions and for each action figure out
the expected utility and then uh choose
the action with the highest expected
utility. Um and then the utility nodes
as I said can have parents uh that uh
give us the value of different states of
the world.
Okay. So here's the algorithm right? We
we take whatever evidence we have we fix
those variables. Then you loop through
the possible actions. You fix the action
node A. you compute
uh the
um posterior distribution
P of W in this case W is the parents of
the utility node. So the P of W given
the evidence and the action that you
choose right so that's where the baset
comes in in general this could be a very
very complicated network right might be
describing a nuclear reactor your
decision is you know should I shut down
the nuclear reactor or allow it to
continue operating uh so it could be a
very very complicated decision depending
on lots and lots of things and the baset
will do all of that it will calculate
for you the probability distribution for
each possible combination of values for
the parents of the utility node. Okay.
And then given a probability for each
combination of parent values, you can
calculate by summing over those values
the probability times the utility. Okay?
So that gives you the expected utility
of of the action A and then you pick the
action with the highest utility. Okay,
so it's conceptually very
straightforward and almost all the work
is going to be done by the baset
inference algorithm that's computing
this posterior distribution.
Okay.
Um so let's look at exactly how that
works in our model.
Right? That's the algorithm again. Um
and let's say we've observed that the
forecast is bad and now we want to know
should we take the umbrella or not.
Okay. Um so here are the uh
probabilities and utilities for this
model. So uh the weather has a prior
probability of 70% for sunshine.
Um the forecast is not uh is not a
perfect predictor. uh the probability
that the forecast is bad uh given that
the weather is actually sunny right is
uh 17% and if the weather is actually
rainy the probability that the forecast
is bad is 77%. So it's not it's not a
perfect predictor of the weather um but
it's reasonably good.
Okay. Um, and notice just right once
again notice the direction of this
arrow,
right?
That it's the it's the weather
situation, right? So when you um when
you get a weather forecast, it's
actually the result of a bunch of
satellites measuring stuff in the
weather, right? So in California, they
look at what's coming from uh from the
west, right? uh from the Pacific Ocean.
Usually the weather is coming in from
the Pacific Ocean. If there's uh a huge
pile of very wet clouds, then they can
predict that it's going to rain in 14
hours time depending on the speed of the
wind and so on. So uh it's the weather
that's actually causing uh the forecast
here. So you think of the forecast as a
as a as a measurement, right? It's a
consequence of something happening in in
the sort of generalized weather system.
If we were being more
um
more accurate about this, right, we'
probably have a markoff model for the
weather and we would say, well, the
forecast is produced by the weather that
was measured already uh plus some
predictions and then we also have our
own predictions about how the weather
might evolve. But here is this is
simplified. Okay. Um the interesting
part is the utility table. So remember
for the utility we're just going to say
what if I knew the weather. What if I
knew the umbrella, right? Um so these
are just deterministic numbers, right?
So if I leave my umbrella at home and
the weather is sunny, that's the perfect
situation because I don't have to lug it
around and I don't get wet. So that's
100. If I leave my umbrella at home and
it rains, then that's zero, right?
That's the worst case because then I get
soaked walking to class.
If I take my umbrella and it's sunny,
well, it's a bit of a pain. Uh if I take
my umbrella uh and it rains,
well, it's still not great uh because
don't like the rain very much. Uh but at
least I'm not getting wet, but I am I am
having to carry the umbrella. So, those
are the utilities.
And now uh let's look at uh calculating
uh the um the expected utility from each
action. So if we choose leave, right?
Then um the expected utility for leaving
given that the forecast is bad, we're
going to sum over those W's, right? And
here the W's are in fact the weather,
right? That's the only uh random
variable that's apparent of the utility
function. Um and so
um
so so the these are the probabilities
computed from the baset basically
applying bay rule to invert the the uh
the arrow and so we find that uh the
probability that it's sunny given that
we've already seen a bad forecast is 34%
and the probability of rain is one minus
that so 66%. Okay. So then we take 34%
times the ideal outcome,
which is where it doesn't rain and we
don't have to carry our umbrella. That's
166%
times the the worst outcome because we
left our umbrella at home and now it's
raining. Uh and so the expected value of
leaving the umbrella at home when the
forecast is bad is 34. All right.
If we take the umbrella,
same thing except that we've got 34%
chance of 20, a 66% chance of 70. And so
the expected value of taking the
umbrella when the forecast is bad is 53.
Okay, so the network tells us that uh
when the forecast is bad, we should take
the umbrella to work. Okay, as one would
hope, right? Now, interestingly,
sometimes
you can have a situation where uh when
the forecast is bad, it says take your
umbrella. When the forecast is good, it
says take your umbrella, right? Uh and
that's particularly true if the forecast
is not very reliable, right? Then you
got this big risk of getting a zero in
both cases and so you end up taking
umbrella. So there the weather forecast
is useless, right? because it doesn't
whatever it tells you, you're still
going to do the same thing. Okay? Um
and and this is a real a real real real
problem particularly when uh if you
think about a nuclear reactor for
example,
right? So nuclear reactor is designed
to fail
once in 10 million years.
Okay? So it's extremely reliable.
So, if you have a warning light on your
nuclear reactor saying, "I'm about to
fail. I'm about to fail."
Right? Now, if that warning light
itself fails once every 10,000 years,
right, which is incredibly reliable for
any kind of light bulb, right? Most
light bulbs only last a thousand hours.
Okay?
Well, when that light uh is is flashing,
it's probably that uh the the monitor
itself, the detector, the failure
detector is failing or uh if there is a
bad condition, the detector light bulb
isn't going to work because it's already
failed. And so to be a useful detector
of a nuclear reactor that's about to
fail,
the detector itself has to be
approximately as reliable as the nuclear
reactor, right? Otherwise, you're just
going to ignore it. You're going to say,
"Oh, it's just probably just the uh the
detectors on the blink, right?"
And so um
uh yeah so this this is a problem you
know as your as the thing you're
measuring gets more and more reliable as
a failure gets rarer and rarer your
detector has to get better and better
for it to be useful at all.
Okay.
So that was a uh that was a very very
simple network. And
notice that that network had
um
uh the utility node with one of the
action nodes directly as a parent.
Okay. Now when we've talked about
utility, we've actually talked about
utilities of states and there are really
two different kinds of quantities and a
lot of literature doesn't really keep
them separate. Um
a function that maps an action and a
state to a value
is called a you already saw this in in
the discussion of MDPs and reinforcement
learning, right? So what's a function
that takes a state and an action and
gives you a value?
You take out the take out your notes.
Okay. There were two kinds of value
thingies that you studied in MDPs and
RL,
right? There's the V,
right? And the V and the U are the same,
right? They're just V is what they call
utility in operations research. That's
why it's just but it's the same thing.
Okay. So there's V and there's Q.
All right. So Q values or Q functions
give you the value of taking an action
in a state. Okay. So um in decision
networks you can have nodes that have
actions as parents that give you value.
Those are really Q value nodes. Um and
uh and this in this formulation of that
of that model right what we've done is
we've we've made explicit
the random variables
uh that actually
are constitutive of your utility
function. Right? So your utility
function doesn't actually care what
action you did.
Right? It's something about the world.
something about the state resulting from
the action is what you care about,
right? The action is just a number if
you like. A1, A2, A3. I don't care. I'm
not more upset because I chose A2. I'm
more upset because A2 produced an
outcome that I didn't like. Okay. So
um so if you want to have a pure utility
function then you need to put in random
variables for the um the states that
result from the action. So here we've
still got the the umbrella action. Um
and we've got the two things that you
might care about, right? One is whether
or not you get wet and the other one is
whether or not you feel stupid carrying
an umbrella around when it's perfectly
dry and sunny. Okay. And so
uh so here we've taken the same uh the
same information and uh and put it into
uh a pure utility function. So the
values are the same and we've got but we
just have different combinations of uh
outcomes for those state variables.
Okay. And generally,
not always, but generally, this is going
to be a more concise way to describe
what's going on.
Okay? That you should think about value
information that we humans can specify
in terms of states of the world of
variables that describe the world that
we care about. And then separate from
that, you have transition models that
describe what actions do. Okay? And if
you mix those two together to get a Q
function, which you can, it's often
going to be the case that the Q function
is much less concise.
So to give you an example, right, the
transition model for chess is maybe half
a page.
The
utility function for chess is maybe two
lines, right? Have I checkmated my
opponent or am I stalemated in a draw?
Right. Um the Q function for chess,
it's about 10 to the 38 pages,
right? Because there's somewhere around
10 to the 40 states in that you can
possibly reach in chess. Um, and the Q
function basically has to tell you, um,
for every one of those states, uh, and
the maybe 30 or 40 actions that you can
do in those states, uh, does that action
win or lose the game eventually, if you
continue playing optimally after that?
Okay, so the Q function becomes a giant
lookup table for all possible states
that you could reach and it's incredibly
um so it's incredibly larger than the
representation in terms of the utility
function and the transition model.
Okay, this is a really important lesson,
right? And it's it's basically why
intelligent entities such as human
beings know things
because if we could always just
represent a policy or a Q function
concisely, we would just learn the
policy or Q function directly and we
would never need to know physics or
chemistry or sociology or AI or
anything, right? Because we would just
behave according to the policy that we
had learned.
All right. Uh, good said that. Okay. So,
value of information
is uh is a very cool thing and uh also
invented by vonoman. Uh, so it appears
in his 1944 book. Um,
and uh, and as I said, it tells you how
valuable it is to find out a piece of
information.
So let's say we start out with our
decision network and we don't know the
forecast and the question is should we
get the forecast
right
maybe
I have to pay for the forecast or maybe
I have to get up out of my chair and
turn the radio on to get the forecast.
Okay
I know you guys don't do that. You just
look on your phone but imagine just for
the sake of argument. Um
okay so um
so we can calculate if we have no
information right we can do the same
thing we did before calculate the
expected value of leaving the umbrella
at home or taking it to work and we find
that uh the expected value of leaving
given no evidence at all right so empty
uh is 70 uh the value of taking it to
work is 35
and so uh absent any information, we're
going to leave the umbrella at home.
So now the question is, is it worthwhile
to find out the weather forecast? And
how valuable is it to do that,
right? And so in words,
um
it's a pretty simple concept, right? You
say, "Well, if I knew that the weather,
if that's sorry, that if I knew that the
forecast was bad, then here's what I
would do.
And would that be better or worse than
what I'm currently planning to do, which
is to leave it at home? If the weather
forecast turns out to be good, what
would I do? And would that be better or
worse than what I'm currently planning
to do?" Well, okay. Yeah. So, I can
figure out how much better or how much
worse each of those outcomes would be
under those two different forecasts. Of
course, I don't know what the forecast
is going to be because I haven't found
it yet, right? And so, I take the
expected value of those two things
weighted by the probability of what the
forecast is likely to tell me. Okay? So,
uh so that's that's the basic idea,
right? And it's actually very
straightforward and and I hope you can
see that all of those things I just
talked about we can just compute from
the decision network uh in the same way
we've already done it. Okay. So what if
you look at the forecast? Well, if the
forecast is good, right, we can
calculate the utilities that we uh in
fact leaving your umbrella at home uh
becomes even better. Right now it's 89
uh versus 25 for taking it to work. So
that's if the forecast is good, right?
If the forecast is um bad, then
uh we can do the calculation uh as we
already did. These are the same numbers
we had before. And so the best choice is
to take the umbrella uh to take the
umbrella to work. Okay. So now we have
if the forecast is good then we will
leave the umbrella at home and our
expected utility will be 89. If the
forecast is bad we're going to take it
to work and our expected utility is 53.
Okay. Now we look at well what how
likely is it that the forecast is going
to be good and bad. Okay.
And we calculate that from the baset and
it says 65% chance you're going to get
forecast of good 35% chance you're going
to get forecast bad. Okay. So then you
take the weighted average of these two
right the values that you expect to get
if you had the information and uh
and that gives you so 65* 89.35*
53 so that gives you 76.4 four.
Okay, so if you didn't have the
information, your value was 70.
If you did have the information, your
expected value would be 76.4. And so the
value of finding out the forecast is 6.4
in this case, $640 or whatever you want
to think of it, whatever your currency
is. Okay,
so that's a very cool thing, right? So
it says that this decision network not
only contains the information you need
to make a decision about the actions,
but it also contains the information you
need to make a decision about what
information to get or at least whether
it's worth getting any particular piece
of information. And you can do that
calculation for all the different things
you could get. Like if you're a doctor,
you know, there's 2,000 different tests
you can order. uh there's 500 ways you
can prod the patient and and another
5,000 questions you could ask the
patient. So you got a lot of possible
actions and you got to choose from all
those actions, right? So I should say
from all those information gathering
actions,
right?
Which information should we gather?
Is any of it worth having? Should we
stop gathering information? So if all of
those pieces of information have value
zero, right? In other words, there's no
more information I could gather that
would change my mind
about telling this patient to go home
and stop bugging me. Right? If that's
the decision I'm making and there's
nothing that's going to change my mind,
then I can say, "All right, I'm I'm
done. Go home and stop bugging me." Yes.
I'm sorry, which values?
>> Oh, so I just um I did the same kind of
calculation I did on the previous slide.
So just summing over the possible values
of weather,
the probability that the weather is
good, probability of weather is bad, the
the utility of taking the umbrella or
leaving the umbrella when the weather is
good or bad. Okay, it's just the the
reason you get different numbers here is
because we before we had forecast is
bad, but um now we don't have any
information. So it's it's a slightly
different probabilities that you get.
Okay.
All right.
So that's the value of information. Uh
the difference between the decision you
expect to make given the information and
the decision you would make without the
information.
Okay. Um,
and so here's another here's an
interesting example of applying value of
information to the Ghostbusters.
Oops.
I can get this to work. Why is it not
playing? There we go.
Okay. So I I I can't figure out how to
get the volume up from my laptop. So uh
I'll just do the narration. Peter Aiel
is speaking from the grave. And right so
this is the prior probabilities, right?
We're going to try to find um the ghost
and uh there's a cost for each probe
that you make. uh there's a bonus for
getting it right and there's a penalty
for getting it wrong if you do a bust
and you're in the wrong place. So the
the system calculates which place is the
best place to look first and it turns
out that that is the best place to look
first. In fact, well there's four of
those squares in the four corners and
those give you more expected utility
than any other square. Right? So you do
that you get a yellow and now you can
see the posterior. Then you just do it
again.
Okay. And uh so we do it again, we get a
red and then uh we go right away and and
do a bust, right? And so it's doing a
bust even though the probability is only
08. So it's calculating that there's no
point in collecting more information
given the cost of taking another turn.
Okay.
Okay. So he's going to do it again with
a more uh a more difficult uh sequence
basically
right so again in the prior situation
these are the best squares it goes here
but this time we got a green and so
green means it's uh the ghost is a long
way away so all the probability is in
the top right okay and that was
surprising that it chose the top left
corner but you know that's that's the
most useful information to get right.
And uh so now it goes tried to get
closer. Now it's found that um
that it's over in this corner. Uh it
does another probe. It has a 47. So now
it's got a choice, right? Should I go
with a 47 or shall I do it again? So it
does one more probe, gets another red,
and now it's 0 98 and then it busts.
Okay.
So
Uh so this concept of value of
information is uh really really useful
right and here are just three examples
right so
oil company uh wants to decide
uh you know should I um should I in
invest invest in this in the drilling
rights for a piece of land or should I,
you know, uh get get into uh full-on
exploitation mode and start drilling
wells. Uh well, before you do that,
because these things cost hundreds of
millions of dollars,
you can uh you can do much cheaper
information gathering, right? You can do
uh seismic measurements where you
basically uh have a something on the
surface either an explosion or a sort of
a thumper uh that that makes a noise and
then you measure how that noise
propagates through the rocks and that
tells you something about what's under
the ground. You can do lowcost test
drilling just to see what's in uh what's
under under the ground. Um and uh you
can pay consultants
uh you can look at satellite images.
There's all kinds of ways of gathering
information and this is really really
high stakes. So uh so oil companies
generally go through the calculations to
figure out uh what's the optimal
sequence of uh tests and information
gathering uh to to participate in
uh exploration and production. uh
doctors well
doctors don't always behave optimally I
would say but they face this problem
right and they're often um
uh following you know sort of textbook
strategies
and um when people have built
probability models for uh you know
certain classes of patients that a
doctor sees uh the available information
that the doctor could collect the
possible actions that the doctor could
do in terms of prescribing or treating.
Um they find that actually doctors are
quite suboptimal.
Um, and uh, the only way that you can
get the algorithm to actually behave in
the same way as the doctor is to put in
a huge amount of disutility
for the doctor
failing to notice that the patient has a
particular disease.
So, it's not that the patient suffers,
it's that the doctor's embarrassed. So
if you put in the doctor's embarrassment
for failing to detect the disease, uh
then your value of information
calculation mimics the doctor's behavior
pretty well. Um and then of course you
do this all the time, right? As you walk
around, your visual system, your hearing
is constantly collecting information uh
actively, right? You're you're moving
your head. uh your uh your auditory
system is attending to certain sounds
and ignoring other sounds uh because uh
they they your your eyes and your ears
want to contribute to your well-being.
Um and so that's that's how they
function is essentially value of
information.
Okay, so it's a very important concept
for rational behavior. Um so this is the
general formula, right? We call it the
value of perfect information for
obtaining
an evidence variable EI given that we've
already seen evidence E, right? And so
it's remember you you don't yet have EI.
So you're going to have to sum over the
possible values of EI, right? the
probability of seeing each of those
values
and then uh the the maximum the value of
the maximum utility action if you had
both E and EI right so the action that I
would do if I observe that right and so
this is the expected utility you're
going to have after observation this is
the expected utility you have before the
observation so the VPI is the difference
between those two things.
Okay. Um
so maybe this is the most famous theorem
about information.
The value of perfect information is non-
negative.
So why why is that? Anyone
can anyone give me a one-s sentence
proof.
Yes.
There's no way that knowing more
information should hurt you. That's a
yes. That's a good intuition. Um, and
you could you could put it in a slightly
uh more expounded way, which is to say
in the worst case, right, I could just
ignore the information. I always have
the option to just ignore the
information and do exactly what I was
going to do before,
right? And so since I always have that
option, I'll only switch if it's a good
idea for me to switch. and therefore um
the expected value of information is
non- negative. Now, interestingly, it
turns out not to be true in game
theoretic situations.
So, there are certain types of games,
meaning decisions involving two or more
agents
uh where knowing more makes it more
difficult for those agents to figure out
a cooperative solution to the game.
Okay. Now, it's not it's not always
true. There are plenty of games where
you can show that this theorem holds,
but there are cases where knowing less
is better.
Okay. Um it's
it's tempting to think, oh well, you
know, if it's worth 10 to get this and
it's worth 17 to get that, then it's
worth 27 to get both of them, right? You
might think, okay, just just like, you
know, if it's worth 10 to get an apple
and 17 to get an orange, then it's worth
27 to get the apple and the orange,
right? But that's not the case for
information. Uh, and trivally, you can
see that if if uh two pieces of
information are essentially identical,
right? So, I can uh I can look and see
if the coin has come up heads. I can
look again to see if the coin has come
up heads, right? And maybe the first
time it's worth something, but the
second time it's not worth very much
because I already looked. And so looking
again hardly changes anything. Okay? So
it's not additive. And it can be the
case that one piece of information by
itself
isn't enough to change your decision,
right? That there's no there's no no
outcome for that variable that would
lead you to change your decision. And so
its VPI would be zero. And you could
have another variable whose VPI is zero.
But if you knew the value of both of
those variables,
then uh they would have positive VPI.
Right? So it can be the case that
individual variables by themselves are
not enough to change your decision. But
having both of them there would be some
chance of changing your decision. And so
it doesn't behave in a nice uh in a nice
compositional way, right? And so that
means that the algorithm just says
choose a piece of information with the
highest VPI
and keep doing that.
It does not necessarily guarantee
optimal behavior.
Okay. And I think that's uh that's an
important thing to remember.
Um but it is order independent, right?
So the value of getting one thing and
then another is the same regardless of
which order you get those two things.
Okay? So you should think of the
evidence variables as sets, right? And
so you've got the value of a set of
evidence variables. Uh and so you don't
have to think about the orderings.
Okay, any questions about that?
Okay, I guess it's all crystal clear.
Great.
Good. Okay. So now we're going to talk
about machine learning
and um
I'll start by just saying what learning
is uh is about. So we're going to cover
this idea of learning in machines which
just means anything that improves the
performance of the agent. So agent and
performance are things we've already
introduced at the beginning of the class
and learning is anything any process for
improving performance as a result of
experience.
Okay. Um now
a lot of what you will see and read uh
as to talk as being machine learning
machine learning is this thing right is
actually an ex you know one very narrow
corner of the whole field of machine
learning okay so reinforcement learning
is one corner of uh of machine learning
what I'm going to talk about today
supervised learning is another corner
right what large language models are
doing is an even smaller corner, right?
It's the a smaller corner of supervised
learning. Um there are lots of other
kinds of learning that we're not even
going to be able to touch on, but some
of them are uh talked about in the book.
Uh one of the kinds of learning that
humans do all the time is compiling,
right? So when we uh when we figure
something out
through a complicated process, right, we
save it away.
Sometimes we try to generalize it. So we
save it away as a general rule so that
anytime I'm faced with a similar
situation in future, I don't have to
figure it all out from scratch, I
already know how to do it, right? And so
that's another kind of learning that's
absolutely ubiquitous in humans um that
uh we're not going to be able to cover
in this class. Um and in fact none of
the companies purporting to do machine
learning actually do that kind of
learning at all. So, so their language
models, right, which are consuming a
vast quantity of electricity, right,
they're asked the same question over and
over again all over the world.
And every time they're asked that
question, they're doing the same
reasoning, right? Um, and uh, and so
they're not learning from that kind of
experience uh, how to avoid doing all
those expensive calculations.
uh the next time. Okay.
All right. Um so so today we'll talk
about this this um idea of generalizing
from experience and then uh how we can
apply that to what's called supervised
learning. So supervised learning meaning
I'm learning a function and I have
examples of the input and output of that
function. So supervised in the sense
that someone tells me what the right
output should be for that input.
Okay. And we'll look at two kinds of
supervised learning method. One is
decision tree learning. The other one is
linear regression which I think is going
to be uh next time. Uh then we'll talk
about basian learning. Uh and then we'll
talk about deep learning which is the
currently popular method of uh of
machine learning. Um after that I think
Dan is going to talk about
um
large language models. So an application
of deep learning to uh prediction in uh
word sequences.
Okay. And as I mentioned we're covering
just a small fraction. There's lots more
classes. So 189 is sort of the basic
theory of machine learning. 182 is sort
of a bit more hands-on deep learning
systems. 180 is uh computer vision which
is these days almost entirely machine
learning. Uh in fact almost all branches
of AI these days are almost entirely
machine learning. Um and I feel sorry
for people who work in computer vision
or even natural language because they
don't get to do computer vision or
natural language anymore.
Right? Computer vision people used to
learn all about geometry and surfaces
and illumination and shading and edges
and texture and all kinds of cool things
and visual physiology and and it's such
a wonderful discipline and now computer
vision is just shove all the images into
a deep network
right uh and so I feel sorry for them
and same with language people used to
study the semantics of language the
syntax the different kinds of languages
that humans have produced all over the
world. Um, all kinds of cool stuff. Um,
all gone. But anyway, it's still it's
still there. Uh, it's just um you have
to take make more effort to to find out.
Okay. So, learning is
an important part, right? So, not all
animals learn.
Um, one of my colleagues
did some interesting experiments with
flies.
So when when a human loses a limb,
right, they have to learn
to, you know, to locomote or pick things
up, you know, with the the new
configuration that they have. Um,
so he thought, let let's see what
happens. It's a bit of an odd thing,
right? So, let's see what happens if I
if I chop off the the wing tip of a fly
while it's flying.
Right. How long does it take to learn
how to fly with this modified wing?
Right. So, he's got a very clever
experimental setup and he can use a
laser beam to to just chop the end off
the wing of the fly as it's flying.
And uh and the answer is one wing beat.
That's how long it takes. One wing beat.
So it modifies its wingbeat pattern. All
the neuromuscular
activations that allow it to fly within
one wing beat,
right? So it doesn't it doesn't learn,
right? It's in some sense pre-programmed
for for that uh eventuality.
And uh so we see this in a lot of
animals. They they're born uh you know
even big animals like gnus right they
they're born they sort of drop onto the
grass and then they get up and run away
right they don't learn to walk
they're born being able to walk.
So uh it's it's kind of interesting
right? And actually pre-term humans
can walk, right? Not very well, but at
if if the baby is born around seven
months, um you can hold them up and
their legs will move like they're
walking, but then they forget that
again. And then when they're if they're
born at full term, uh they have to go
through the whole long slow process of
of learning to walk. So So why? Well,
you know what? One one point is well,
you know, when when animals or AI
systems are born,
they don't know about the world, right?
Whoever made them decided
or whether it's evolution or something
else, right? At least for humans decided
to have uh human babies just have to
learn everything,
right? We're not born. People used to
think that babies were born knowing
Latin,
right? And and they did experiments
where they would literally not allow
anyone to speak to the baby and then
they would wait for the baby to start
speaking Latin. And uh because they
thought Latin is the perfect language.
So like I don't know, 1100 AD or
something like that. So uh so needless
to say that didn't happen.
Um
and uh
you know we do have some stuff built in,
right? Um so we we have eye tracking
built in. So when you move your finger
in front of the newborn baby's eyes, uh
you'll see their eyes following their
finger. Um there's some kind of face
recognition built in. So they respond to
human faces as newborn babies, right?
they don't. You can make other shapes
and they don't respond in the same way.
So, we're beginning to by by these
experiments like what do they attend to?
How long do they look at something
before they get bored and look at
something else? Uh we can start to see
what newborn babies know, but it's not a
huge amount.
Um and and so this is it because I guess
um we're intended to be extremely
flexible to to live in a vast range of
environments and circumstances
and uh and so we've found this
evolutionary niche where it's it's worth
spending 10 or 15 years becoming capable
uh as long as our parents can stand us
for that long. um then they look after
us and then we can become capable
adults. Other animals they're in a
different niche. They don't learn at
all. Okay. Another justification um
comes from uh Alan Turing's 1915 paper
the computing machinery in the mind. So
he basically says I think we should
build AI systems using machine learning
right rather than uh trying to program
all the behaviors of an intelligent
system. Uh we should have a uh a
learning mechanism
and start out as a blank slate and then
learn everything from there. Right? And
so um so what we found over the years in
AI is that for some tasks not for all uh
for some tasks uh learning is the best
practical engineering method of getting
a high performance system right so
for example it's not that we don't know
how to play go
we just found that reinforcement
learning was the best way to get a high
performance go program. Uh that was not
true for chess, right? Learning
reinforcement learning for chess hasn't
worked that well until very recently. So
we got to world championship performance
in chess uh largely by hand engineering
the program. Right? So we had search
algorithms which is basically similar to
the one that Alph Go uses but search
algorithms with an evaluation function
that's handcoded. Um, and that uh that's
enough to beat human beings.
Okay. But if you think about like how if
I say the word cat
and then I say the word cut,
you immediately tell the difference.
How do you tell the difference?
Right? Beats me, right? And so for that
kind of thing, you know, even though I
can do it, I can't tell you how to do
it. I can't turn it into an algorithm.
And so, uh, machine learning is the only
practical way, uh, of getting a system
that can do those kinds of things.
Okay. So people have tried to build
learning systems for a long time. Not
just in AI but even before that people
built mathematical models of human
learning. Um and then they applied the
well human learning and animal learning.
Um this is BF Skinner
who was the the leading American
exponent of behaviorist psychology. So
behaviorist psychology models all uh
living beings as stimulus response
mechanisms.
So you put in a stimulus, you get a
response and learning consists of
training that response to be more
adaptive, right? To be more suitable to
the stimulus. And so here is Skinner
training pigeons. And during the war
they trained pigeons to they put them in
missiles.
Uh and the pigeons had a little window
and they they pecked on the window. The
window was sort of a touch sensitive
screen and so the pigeon could guide the
missile to the target by pecking on the
screen. So they trained pigeons to do
that uh during during World War II
because they didn't have AI. So they had
to use pigeons, right? But using
stimulus response training, uh, they
were able to get the pigeons to do that.
So, pretty amazing. Um, and then he also
applied it to his own daughter, Debbie.
So, there she is in in the same kind of
Skinner training box. Um, I'm not sure
what she was being trained to do. So,
interestingly, all right, you think, "Oh
my goodness, this is so terrible." But
they interviewed Debbie later and she
said, "Oh, no, it was fine. You know, I
learned a lot. They were, you know, I
was perfectly happy." Um but she was
trained in these boxes for for most of
her childhood. Anyway um okay so this is
some of the earliest learning machines.
You can see there it says perceptron. So
perceptrons are extremely simple neural
networks. Um this is Frank Rosenblat who
developed the perceptron learning
algorithm and also then uh actually
created physical devices that
implemented that learning algorithm. Um,
so each of these is uh one perceptron.
So if you put
uh you know if you put 64 of those in a
big square then you might be able to
train them to recognize a character or
something like that. Okay. So um perhaps
it doesn't look very promising now,
right? But uh at the time newspapers
said, "Oh my goodness, you know, the
beginning of super intelligent
machines." uh with these big clunky one
bit learning systems.
Okay. So when you think about machine
learning
um
you have to think really
what kind of agent am I going to be
improving?
Right? We don't really have a way to
just
do what Turing said, which is start from
a completely blank
slate.
Okay. Um,
you could try that. In fact, in the 50s,
people did try that. They tried um they
tried to evolve for programs.
So what they did was they they had a
fitness function. So they had the 4chan
program had to do something. Imagine
like it had to play a video game, right?
And if it was good at the video game,
then it got to have more offspring. So
you took pairs of 4R programs, you mix
up their code to produce new 4chan
programs. And uh the programs that did
well on the video game would get to have
more offspring. Um and they hoped that
by doing that um they would eventually
get four programs that were incredibly
intelligent.
Right? So they they really were starting
from scratch in the sense that any
program could have come out of that.
Right? And in principle they were right.
That process could have produced super
intelligent machines because
by definition for you know forran is a
Turing equivalent programming language.
So anything that is a super intelligent
machine can be written as a forran
program. And so in principle that
process could eventually have produced
super intelligent machines,
right? Uh it didn't.
And um at the time people thought oh you
know the reason it doesn't is because
for programs are very fragile that when
you make a small change to a for program
most of the time it just stops working
right somehow DNA is a bit more robust
when you make a small change to DNA it
doesn't the organism doesn't stop
working might not be an improvement but
it doesn't usually completely disable
the organism. uh whereas forchan
programs right if you change an x to a y
and y isn't uh isn't initialized then
the program just stops working and so um
so that was the theory but in fact
the computers they were using
were about 100 trillion times slower
than what you would typically use
nowadays.
Um, so had we done those experiments on
machines a 100red trillion times more
powerful, who knows what would have
happened, right? I don't think they're
going to try it, but you never know. Um,
anyway, so generally speaking, we
instead of starting from a completely
blank slate, we have in some sense a
template, right? This is the agent type
that we're going to build. And then you
got to figure out okay which piece of
the agent are we going to learn? Um and
sometimes you can learn all the pieces
sometimes you fix some of the pieces and
you learn other pieces. I'll give you
some examples in a sec. Right? Then you
think okay for that piece how am I going
to represent that piece? Is it going to
be a linear function? Is it going to be
a decision tree? Is it going to be a
two-layer neural net? Is it going to be
a transformer neural net? Is it going to
be u something else? you know, a cubic
polomial. Uh there's all kinds of ways
of representing functions. Maybe it's
just a piece of Python. Um then you ask,
okay, if I'm going to learn that piece,
what data, what experience bears on that
learning process? What can I use uh as
experience to make that piece better? Um
and then the last question is, you know,
what do I already know about how that
piece should operate, right? Can I put
some of uh my human knowledge or
knowledge obtained from another learning
process to uh essentially bootstrap to
get it off the ground quickly to
constrain the learning process so that
uh it learns faster? Uh what what
information do we have that we could
use?
So here's a few examples,
right? So
uh the first one uh my agent's going to
be an MCTS search algorithm. So it's I'm
going to train it to play a game like Go
or chess. Okay. The thing that I'm going
to improve
is the evaluation function or the the
value network uh as it's called in Alph
Go, right? There's basically two pieces
to MTS. There's the policy network that
chooses which rollouts to do and then uh
or which branch to to follow and then
the evaluation function that takes the
terminal nodes of the tree and
approximates their true value.
Uh and you can learn either of those
pieces. But if we're going to learn the
evaluation function, you got to decide
how do we represent it, right? And we
might say, you know, a good
old-fashioned
uh computer game representation would
just be a linear function. So you've got
some features of the board uh and you
take a linear combination of those
features with weights. And so the thing
you're going to learn is the weights.
Um what feedback do you have? Right?
What is the experience? The data. Now
when you're playing go or chess, there's
no data telling you, hey, that weight
should be six,
right? The only data you get is you
lost. You're lost. you lost, you won,
right? That's the data you get. And so
that's a reward signal. So then you're
looking at some kind of uh reinforcement
learning algorithm. Okay. Um what did we
start with? Well, for for Go and chess,
uh for Alph Go, for deep blue and so on,
um we knew the rules of the game, right?
So we didn't have to learn the
transition model, okay? Because that's
another piece that you could learn. Um,
if you playing an unknown game, right?
So, um, you pick up a new video game,
you you don't know the rules of the
game. You don't know what's going to
happen, right? And so, you start playing
with the buttons and you see, right? As
a human being, you know an awful lot
about video games that you've never
played.
Can you think of an example?
Right.
So, what happens when you press the
button that says left?
Does the Does your character go up? No,
your character goes to the left. Right.
Um,
you know, are gold coins good or bad?
Right? Would you expect that if you
picked up a gold coin,
you would be poisoned and you would die
three turns later, right? No. You have a
pretty good idea that uh gold coins are
things you're supposed to pick up,
right? So, you just know tons and tons,
right? You uh you know that
uh space is roughly continuous
uh and 2D, right? So, you know that if
you keep going left, you'll you'll move
left. And if you go back to the right,
you'll move right, right? And this the
space that you're in doesn't grow and
shrink and uh and uh develop holes and
all kinds of stuff like that. So,
there's just a huge amount of basic
knowledge of let's call it video game
physics, uh video game value systems, uh
video game iconography, uh that you
bring to the game already.
Okay. Uh so if you're um you know if
you're looking at uh an agent for
solving an MDP in general,
right? There's uh there's the reward
function. Uh and there's the transition
model. That's what you need to know. Uh
you could try to learn a policy
directly. You could try to learn a Q
function. You could try to learn a V
function. Right? So there's lots of
different things you could learn. But
let's say we're just going to learn the
transition model.
Okay? we're going to be really boring
and represent that as a transition
matrix, right? So just states, states,
transition probabilities between them
for each action. Um the advantage you
have here, unlike the MCTS search where
you're trying to learn the value, is
that you see the outcome. So you take an
action, you see the state that you get
to, right? So you have in some sense the
correct value for the transition model.
Uh given this state and given this
action, what state do I get to? Oh, this
one. Right? So uh so that learning
problem is much easier than the
reinforcement learning problem in the
previous case. Okay? So I think you get
the idea.
Right? There's um there's generally
three categories of learning that are
commonly studied. As I mentioned there's
there are many many categories of
learning but these are the most common.
So supervised learning we're trying to
learn a function where we have the
correct answer available for each
training instance. So this is uh this is
supervision. So that's um it's telling
you the right answer for the transition.
Uh similarly in a chatbot you're trying
to predict the next word. In the
training data you know the next word
because you can see it. It's right
there. Okay. And so again this is
supervised learning.
uh reinforcement learning you've already
seen where you don't get the correct
action,
right? Um but you get at some point
eventually a reward.
And then there's unsupervised learning,
which is probably, I'd say, the least
well- definfined. Um and it just means
you get data and you're supposed to do
something useful with it, right? Uh an
example of unsupervised learning is is
what uh biologists did for centuries
which is they just observe
all the species on the earth and they
observe that those species seem to have
categories right that there are specific
species and then there are uh genuses
and families and orders and filer and so
on. So there's a um taxonomy of all life
on earth and this was unsupervised
learning. No one told us to do that
right it just was helpful in our
understanding and eventually to make
predictions as well uh of the data that
we're collecting. So this is an example
of unsupervised learning.
Okay. So let's let's do some supervised
learning. Right. So the the basic idea
is we've got some target function f.
Okay, this is f we don't know but we're
going to try to learn what it is. Okay,
we have a training set. So this is the
red stuff is just terminology, right? Uh
so training set is the data from which
you're going to learn this function. Uh
the training set consists of labeled
examples. So x j. So the j is the index
of example. J is 1 2 3 4 5. So the J
example has an input XJ and an output
value YJ. So YJ is the label, right? The
correct answer for the function. Okay?
And so YJ is equal to F of XJ. So you've
got the values of f at particular points
that you've sampled and now you're
trying to figure out, well, what is this
f? And then once you figured it out, you
can use that to get the value of f at
other points that you haven't seen
before. Okay. So for example, um
if I'm trying to learn a giraffe
detector,
right? So f of xj would be one if it's a
giraffe, zero if it's not a giraffe, and
then uh xj itself could be an image.
Right? I I spend a lot of my time on
this problem. So XJ is a seismic signal
or a collection of seismic signals from
detectors all over the world. Uh and
then f of xj would be um is this a
nuclear explosion or an earthquake.
Okay. So um
so really x can be anything at all,
right? It can be a movie and f could be
this is a great movie or a terrible
movie. It could be um it could be a
book, it could be a lecture, it could be
anything at all. Um
and then uh f takes that thing and gives
you some uh some quantity that is the
label.
Now we so as I said we don't get f we
just get the values of f at certain
points and we have to produce a
hypothesis. So the learning algorithm's
job is to generate a hypothesis.
So H refers to the hypothesis that the
algorithm can output. Okay? And we would
like H to be close to F,
right? Ideally it would be exactly F,
but that might be too much to ask for.
But we definitely want it to be close to
F in some sense.
Okay? And uh and roughly what that means
is that if I pick another example from
the input space and feed it into h, I'm
likely to get something that matches f
on that example. Okay? So I want it to
be uh I want the the output to be either
identical to f on that or close to f and
I want that to be true for most of the
cases that I might try uh as inputs.
Okay. So we don't for now we don't have
to be more precise about that. If you're
interested there is a section I think
it's 194
or 19 maybe 19.5 anyway. So the section
on learning theory that makes this more
precise right what we call probably
approximately correct learning and it
talks about whether that's feasible can
you prove that your algorithm will in
fact find hes that are close to f in a
precisely defined sense
okay um so how do you choose this h well
that's why there are so many different
branches of machine learning right even
supervised learning because uh h can
come from all kinds of different
function families right um so
for a long time in statistics
if you went to a statistician and said
hey I've got some data can you fit a
function to it you'd say well I've got
linear regression
that's all I have sorry there's nothing
else linear regression right um and then
maybe it was like well I've got linear
regression or mixture of gaussians which
do you want right And those those are
your two choices. Um now of course we
have much more than that. Uh logistic
regression. So linear models go back
fitting linear models 200 and something
years probably. Um
uh logistic regression
is a is a classifier. Although it says
regression, it's really a classifier. So
it says
yes or no or gives you a probability
that you belong in the yes class or the
no class. Um but it's uh similar to a
linear model. So it takes uh a linear
function of the input attributes and
then does a threshold on that value to
give you the output.
Uh neural networks are just uh giant
tunable circuits. Uh decision trees are
what they sound like. They're functions
represented by branches, you know. So if
this, then if this, then if this, then
if not that, then if this, then the
answer is two, right? And so a whole
collection of if then arranged into a
tree. Um, you can have what are called
nearest neighbor algorithms where you
just take the the query, the new X, and
you say which is the closest X in the
training set, and you return the value
associated with the closest X in the
training set. That's called nearest
neighbor. Works really well for a lot of
problems. Um we have grammarss that take
a sentence and say yes or no. This is
grammatical. Uh and as I said you can
just have programs, right? So functions
can be represented by programs and uh
and there are there's a whole sub branch
of machine learning where people learn
programs from examples.
Okay. Um and there's two more terms. So
classification is uh learning a function
that has a discrete output value.
Regression is learning a function that
has a real valued output value. Okay.
Usually regression also assumes that the
input is a vector of real numbers but
doesn't strictly have to be that way.
But that's that's what's normally
assumed.
Okay. So just for people who like
pictures, right? So, here are some X's.
Here are some FXs. There's a picture of
a giraffe. And indeed, it's a giraffe.
Giraffe. Giraffe. Giraffe. Giraffe.
It's not a giraffe. What is it?
It's a llama.
Okay. So, this is a giraffe llama
detector, right? Does a giraffe or a
llama, right? Only two values. So if you
give it a bus, it's probably going to
say it's a llama, right? So here's some
more another llama. This is also a llama
apparently. Okay. And so now you train
your model, right? You get your H
and uh here's another image and you have
is this giraffe or a llama?
So yeah, that's a giraffe. They have
very long tongues. I had this picture
because it reminded me when I went to
the zoo when I was a kid. I was walking
with my mom and she had an ice cream in
her hand and the giraffe leaned its head
over the fence. This tongue came out
like this long and lit just sucked up
the ice cream off the cone and at it.
So, uh I never never forgot that.
Anyway, all right. So, that's
classification. Very straightforward. Um
so, regression is like you know the the
simplest version of regression is just
fitting a curve to some points on a
graph, right? So, this would be linear
regression. you're fitting a straight
line, a linear model to the data. The
reason it's called regression, it's not
a particularly intuitive word. Uh the
reason it's called regression is
entirely by mistake.
So the first paper that did this had the
word regression
on the picture, but for a different
reason, and everyone thought, oh, this
must be regression. Actually, it's
nothing to do with that at all. But
anyway, got called regression for as a
mistake and that the name stuck ever
since. Um, okay. So, I could fit a
straight line. I could fit a parabola.
Uh, that's a better fit to those five
points. But of course, leaving this one
out altogether. Um, if I want to get all
of those points, I have to have a higher
order polomial. Right? Maybe that's a
good idea. But, you know, with higher
order polinomials, right, they they tend
to go completely bonkers. you know as
you as you get outside the range of the
data uh and it's very very unstable so
uh small change in the data point leads
to a huge change in the function when
you have higher order polinomials right
and I could also fit it with this right
that doesn't look very sensible that
goes through all the data points exactly
right but you would say no one in the
right mind would think that that's a
good way of fitting the data but it's
still a possible hypothesis because it's
still the output of some nonlinear
regression function. Okay? And so the
question for you is well why is that
nonsensical?
Right? What is the right principle for
saying that's ridiculous?
Maybe that's too simple. Maybe this is
just right. Right? What how do we figure
that out?
Okay. So lots of questions, right? Which
hypothesis space we're going to choose?
You want it to be probably reasonably
expressive. So it's got to have a lot of
functions in it. If you ha if you think
the thing you're trying to learn might
be quite complicated, you you got to
have a big hypothesis space. How do you
measure the degree of fit? How well the
function is fitting? Is it okay if it
just uh like you know is it okay if it
leaves one out like that?
Is that all right? Right. That it fits
all but one point and maybe that's an
outlier. That would be one way of
thinking about degree of fit.
Um, and then how do you trade off this
degree of fit with the complexity of the
function,
right? Because you might not be able to
fit all the data perfectly unless you
have an incredibly complicated, messy
function. Maybe you don't want that,
right? Maybe that doesn't feel right or
maybe it's too unstable. And so you got
to somehow trade these things off. And
um this normally goes under the heading
of Okam's razor. So Okam was a uh
British philosopher in the middle ages.
Um, and his his work was mostly
translated into French and a lot of the
though I guess may probably he wrote it
in Latin. But anyway, in the French
editions it's it's written occam
because they didn't have a K and so and
then everyone thought that's how his
name was spelled but his name was
actually spelled O C HM. Okam. Um, so
Okam's razor says
essentially your hypothesis should be no
more complicated than they need to be to
explain the data, right? That you you're
not entitled to add extra curly cues and
wiggles and so on, unless there's some
reason in the data for doing that.
Um, then there's a computational
question, right? So even if I said,
okay, here's a great hypothesis space. I
know how to to trade off degree of fit
against complexity of the function. Now
I want to find the function h that has
the best fit and simplicity.
Right? That's a computational question.
And uh and so what uh what computer
science has done separate from
statistics is actually point out that
there are many classes of functions
where finding the best fit function is
itself intractable.
Right? And so there's not just a
statistical justification for choosing a
class of hypothesis, but there's a
computational reason why you might
prefer one class to another.
Uh and then there's this theoretical
question. So you've got your age, it's a
good fit. What reason do you have to
believe that for some unseen data point,
uh it's going to give you a good
prediction? How confident should you be
in that prediction? How much are you
willing to bet?
Right? And so that's uh that's what
theory uh the theory of learning uh is
all about.
See how we're doing on time. Okay, I
guess that's what we have time for
today. So right, next time we'll do uh
the decision tree learning algorithm and
the linear regression.